Hello and welcome back to our Image and Video Processing class.
大家好 欢迎回到视频和图像处理课程
We are going to continue with image restoration, and so far we have dealt a
我们将要继续图像复原的内容 目前为止
lot with the noise. So let us now work with the filtering
我们处理了噪声相关内容 接下来要学习滤波部分
component. So let us remember that this is the
请记住这是
complete model of degradation that we are talking about.
我们讨论过的完全退化模型
We are talking about filtering the image and then adding noise. And so far we have
我们将要对图像过滤 然后再加上噪声
considered that there was no filtering, but just noise.
现在假设没有滤波 只有噪声
In general, what we have here as we have seen before
通常来说 这里我们会看到的是g(x,y)
is g(x,y). The observed image is equal to f(x,y)
观察到的图像等于f(x,y)
convolution with h(x,y) plus the noise, which, as we discussed before, is a
和h(x,y)的卷积加上噪声 就像以前讨论过的
random violate that we add noise to the image.
我们在图像中加入的噪声其实就是一种随机变化
And we have seen how to try to estimate the noise.
我们已经知道如何来估计噪声
Now let us discuss how to try to estimate this blurring function.
现在让我们来看看如何估计这个模糊函数
In general it's called a blurring function, this h.
通常这里的函数h被称作模糊函数
This is much harder than estimating the noise.
这比估计噪声难得多
But before we discuss that why is this important.
但在我们讨论为什么这很重要之前
Let me just illustrate it as a very, very simple formula why this is important.
让我通过一个非常非常简单的公式来说明为什么这很重要
And for that lets assume for a second that we don't have any noise.
为了方便起见 假设有一刻我们没有噪声
So basically there is no noise. We're going take the Fourier Transforms
因此这里没有噪声了 我们将对其使用傅里叶变换
of this and the Fourier is g of u, v equal f of u, v times.
傅里叶变换结果是G(u,v)等于F(u,v)乘以H(u,v)
H of UV. So for those that are familiar with ,
对于你们中熟悉傅里叶变换的人来说
this is very clear. For those that are not, just bare with me
这很容易 对于不熟悉的人 请先跟着我说的听一下
for a moment. In Fourier, the convolution becomes a
在傅里叶变换中 卷积变成了乘积
product. So basically we have transformed our
这样我们就将图片变换到了另一个域中
image into a different domain where the convolution became a product.
在这个域中卷积转化成了乘积
And now look what we have, we want to estimate the original image so we divide,
来看看我们得到了什么 我们想要估计原始图像 所以我们做除法
so we say okay, very good. F u, v is equal to the observation,
因此很好 我们做到了  F(u,v) 等于 观察图像 (的频谱函数)
basically the degrade, the degraded image divided by the filter.
退化的图片除以滤波器
So if we manage to estimate the filter, all very easy.
如果我们能够估计滤波器 一切都变得简单了
We take the observed image, we do our Fourier transform, we do our Fourier
我们获取观察到的图片 并进行傅里叶变换
transform of the estimated filter. We divide one by the other.
对估计的滤波器进行傅里叶变换 我们将一个除以另一个
We got the original image, actually it's Fourier transform, we invert it, we get
我们得到了原始图像 它经过了傅里叶变换 再做逆变换
the image back. This is what's called inverse filtering.
我们重新得到了图像 这就是逆滤波 (inverse filtering)
Has some fundamental problems, in particular because there is no guarantee,
有一些基本问题 尤其是因为我们无法保证
that this H, U, V is always different than zero.
H(u,v)总是非零的
Actually for realistic scenario's, it has either some zeros, or is very close to
对于真实场景来说，它存在一些零点 UV取某些值时它会非常接近零
zero for some values of U or V, but the general idea is very, very good that we
但是这个整体思路是非常好的
basically if we have knowledge about this degradation function, then we can try to
如果我们知道了退化函数 就能尝试做逆变换
invert it. And that's very cool.
这很酷
I mean it's that, we want to try to estimate it.
我的意思是 我们想要尝试去估计它 (退化函数)
As I say estimating it very, very hard, much harder than estimating the noise.
就像我说的 估计它是很难很难的 比估计噪声难得多
So let's see some examples where we can actually estimate it and also some
让我们来看看能估计它的一些例子
examples of what type of h functions do we have in reality.
还有一些我们现实中会遇到的 h函数
For example, one thing that happens is, as I mentioned earlier this week, is
比如 这周早些时候我提到过的一个例子
what's called blurring. Blurring means that I basically observe
什么是模糊
an image that is the result of my original image.
模糊表示我观察到的图像 是原始图像卷积上
Convolve, let's say, with the Gaussian function with zero mean uncertain
高斯函数 这些高斯函数均值为零 方差或标准差不确定
variance, or standard deviation. And we already saw the general function
我们已经知道基本的高斯函数
of a Gaussian. Basically, this exponential with a
这个e指数是二次项函数 (具体公式查维基)
quadratic exponential function. We saw it when we were discussing noise.
我们在讨论噪声的时候看到过这个高斯函数
Basically, it blurs my image. Now if you know that there is a Gaussian
它会模糊图像  现在如果你知道有某个高斯函数
function that is affecting your observation.
正在影响你的观察
So this would be my observation. This would be my G.
这就是观察到的图片 这是g函数
If you know that G is the result of F. With a Gaussian filter.
如果你知道 g 是 f 通过高斯滤波器后的结果
And you also know that the F was actually a dot.
那么你就会知道 f 实际上是一个点
A delta function. Just a point, that in that case for
一个 δ函数 也就是一个点
example, that very trivial case, you can actually estimate the blurring.
比如在这个简单的例子中 你能估计模糊函数
Actually, not very hard because a simple property of the convolution says that
实际上这不难 因为卷积有一个简单性质
basically if F is the delta function that is convolved, with G.
如果 f 是 δ函数 它和G做卷积
Then we get G, so basically this is actually the Gaussian. So a very simple
结果得到 G 即高斯函数
case that we can actually estimate our H function for the particular case,
这是个很简单的例子 在这个特定例子中可以估计出h函数
that we have a Gaussian filtering. Now,
在这个例子里我们正好有一个高斯滤波器
this might sound a bit ridiculous, as first.
这乍听起来也许令人奇怪
I say, how do I know that there was a dot, that it was a delta function in my
我是说 我怎么知道图片中有一个点 也就是是一个δ函数的？
image? But actually it is not so ridiculous,
但事实上这并不荒谬
because we can use this to calibrate a system.
因为我们可以利用这个来校准系统
If we know that our camera is blurring. Then I can put artificially an image that
如果我们知道镜头是模糊的 那么可以人为地放一张图片
has a delta function and then I estimate my blurring.
图片上有 δ函数 然后我估计模糊程度
So this is very useful to, to calibration to do estimation of how the camera is
所以这对于调整和评估镜头工作情况很有用
behaving. Very important.
这非常重要
Now I'm going to tell you something else that will further enhance the knowledge
现在我将要告诉你们一些别的事情来增长你们的知识
and the concept why this is a hard function.
以及为什么这是一个难求的函数
A hard function to estimate. If convolution G is equal to G
一个难预测的函数 如果G的卷积等于G和F的卷积
convolution F. So you might wonder is F my original
你也许会有疑问F是我的原始图像吗
image? So was my original image a delta?
我的原始图像是一个δ函数吗
Am I blaring a Gaussian? Or was my original image a Gauissian?
是我模糊了一个高斯函数吗？ 或者换个问法 我的原始图像是一个高斯函数吗？
Am I blaring a delta, which means no blaring.
还是我模糊了一个δ函数 这意味着原始图像并不模糊
So there is a lot of basic ambiguity here that we don't' know which one is what,
所以这里有很多不明确的地方 我们不知道哪一个是对的
and that is yet another challenge that we have when we are trying to estimate the
这也是我们想要估计滤波函数时的另一挑战
filtering function. And normally what you do is you assume
通常你的做法是
models for the image and models for the filtering.
图片的模型和滤波器的模型
But this is just to illustrate how hard this problem is.
但这正显示了解决这个问题是多么困难
So this is an example where we can estimate.
下面说一个预测的方法
Gaussian actually as I say is very important for blaring.
正如我所说 高斯函数对模糊处理非常重要
It's also a model that is very frequently used for turbulence.
它同样也经常用来做湍流的模型
So here is an image which is courtesy of, of, of NASA,
这是一张NASA授权提供给我们的图片
and it appears in the book that we are using so far.
我们一直在用的书里也有
And here we have basically the same image under different levels of turbulence,
这儿我们有同一幅图像分别在不同级别湍流下的照片
from more turbulence to less turbulence. So at least you can observe here the
湍流强度由高到低 至少你可以在这儿看到模糊效应
blurring effect and very often turbulence is modelled with a Gaussian filter.
通常湍流模型用高斯滤波器建立
So it's very, very important, we discussed that Gaussian noise
它相当重要 我们讨论过高斯噪声分布
distributions are very important mathematically although they don't appear
在数学意义上很重要 虽然他们在现实中并不存在
really, in real physical scenarios very often.
但在真实的物理场景中
Gaussian smoothing, Gaussian filtering actually is a very realistic model.
高斯平滑 高斯滤波是非常符合实际的模型
For a lot of things that are happening in physical cameras.
因为很多情形都发生在物理相机中
The other type of blurring that appears a lot is what's called motion blurring.
另一种经常遇见的模糊叫做动态模糊
And the basic idea of motion blurring is that when you're taking a picture if the
动态模糊的主要思想是当你拍一张照片的时候
object is moving. Pictures are taken by integrating the
如果目标是移动的 拍摄得到的照片将整合
light that comes into the sensor. So if the object is moving during your
所有进入感应器的光 所以如果目标在积分时间内移动的话
integration time, basically you get a blurry picture.
你就会得到一张模糊的照片
And that's illustrated here before I write down the formulas.
这里显示的图片就是这种情况 在我写公式之前
So in this case, it's basically a simulation of instead of moving the
在这个例子中 这其实是一个仿真
object, we move the camera. And the basic idea is, going back to our
我们用相机的移动代替目标的移动 基本思路就是考虑g、f函数
GF functions, basically your G function that we are observing is actually the
这里g函数实际就是一个从0到T的积分
integral from zero to T. That's a time of integration of your
t是相机在X方向上的积分时间
camera, of your image at X. But the point X is moving, so I can call
但关键是X方向上是运动的
that function of motion, let's say X of T,
所以称其为运动函数 记作x(t)
to write down that basically it's moving, and it's also moving in the Y direction,
表示它是运动的 它在Y方向上也是运动的
Y of T. And I'm integrating over T.
写作y(t) 同时我对 t 积分
Okay? So basically, what I'm doing here is I'm
好 我现在做的并不是拍一张照片
not taking one image. It's like I've taken multiple images and
这更像拍了很多照片
I'm adding them, and what I see is the result.
把它们加起来 而我看到的是相加后的照片
This actually was simulated by taking this image here,
这可以通过这张拍摄的照片来仿真这个效果
shifting it, let's say, to the right, just by a tiny bit. Shifting it again,
平移 比如向右一点点 再次平移
shifting it again, and then adding that. That's what this operation is doing, is
再平移 然后把它们加起来 这就是这个公式所做的事情
basically adding images on its own shifts.
将照片自身平移后的照片相加
And, this is how we're observation. Now, if we take, if we do the math and we
这也是我们如何观察事物的
take the Fourier transform in both sides, and we use properties of the Fourier
现在如果我们用数学的方法对两边进行傅里叶变换  利用傅里叶变换的性质
transform. Then we can also write this in the form
同样可以写出我们前面看到的那种形式
that we have seen before, G equal H,
g 等于 h 卷积上 f
F. So, also this translation is actually a
所以这里变换其实是一个滤波器
filter, and I am not going to do that but you're more than welcome to do that as an
我这里就不写了 但是欢迎大家自己作为练习
exercise, a very simple exercise, if you are familiar with basic concepts
一个非常简单的练习 如果你熟悉傅里叶变换的基本概念的话
in Fourier transform, you basically just as I say, take the Fourier in both sides,
正如我说的 将两边进行傅里叶变换
and use properties of, of translation. And you get this filter, which of course
使用变换的性质 你将得到这个滤波器
will depend on the velocities. Okay, so you could imagine that if the
当然它和速度有关 所以你可以想象
object is not moving at all, there is no blurring.
如果目标完全没有移动 就不会有模糊了
If the object is moving a lot, there is much more blurring.
如果目标移动很多 就会有更多的模糊
So, this filter will depend on these velocities.
所以这个滤波器将依赖于这些速度
And once again the question will be, just to show how hard it is, how do I estimate
再次提到那个问题 这个问题正显示了估计函数是多么困难 即我如何从这张照片来估计
from this? Both my image and my blurring effects.
估计我的原始图像和模糊效果
Certainly not a trivial thing to do. Even if I knew that the result is a
当然不是一个琐碎的事情 如果我知道这是动态模糊的结果
result of motion blurring. The, the concept is that, from the sum of
动态模糊概念是将多张图片相加求和
multiple images, you have to estimate one.
你需要估计一个
Okay? So that's certainly not a trivial
好 所以这不是一个琐碎的概念
concept. If I give you the number five, and I tell
如果我给你数字5 然后告诉你
you it's the sum of two numbers, there is no way for you to know which two
这是两个数字之和 你不会知道是哪两个数字相加
numbers I added unless I give you more information about that.
除非我告诉你更多的信息
We're going to discuss this more when we talk in a few weeks more advanced topics
我们将会在后面的课程中讨论这些更加深入的话题
in image restoration. When we come back to this topic you'll
也就是关于图像复原 当我们再次回到这个估计问题上时
see different tools like sparsmalling and to expect that.
你将会看到不同的解决工具 例如稀疏矩阵
This is to illustrate that is a hard problem, and an extremely important
这就是为了说明这是一个复杂的问题 同时也是一个非常重要的问题
problem. Simple models like Gaussian de-blurring
简单模型如高斯模糊模型或者动态模糊
or motion, or, Gaussian blurring, sorry. The blurring is the operation of, of
模糊就是进行反相处理
inverting, and motion blur are very, very important.
动态模糊是非常非常重要的
And we need to be able to invert them to go back to our original very, very sharp
我们需要能够通过反求它们 来还原得到非常锐化的原始图像
image. What we're going to do next, is
接下来
basically, we're going to see one way of doing that,
我们将看到一种实现方式
and that's called Wiener filtering. There's one way of inverting a filter and
叫做维纳滤波 有一种方法能反求估计出滤波器或者噪声
inverting noise, and we're going to see that in the next
我们将在下一个视频中看到
video. See you soon.
再见
Thank you.
谢谢大家